Guide to the Thomas Campbell Correspondence THOMAS CAMPBELL CORRESPONDENCE
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Campbell correspondence
1826-1851
GEN MSS 226
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Letters to and from Thomas Campbell. 18 letters to various people, many of them drafts, nine of them to William George Spencer Cavendish, duke of Devonshire. 54 letters to Campbell from various people, including 8 letters from James Thomson Gibson Craig, and 6 letters from Charlotte Townshend Osborne, duchess of Leeds. Accompanied by miscellaneous notes, clippings, theater programs, etc. belonging to Thomas Campbell; in all, 10 items.
Campbell, Thomas, 1790-1858
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James M. Osborn, 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Thomas Campbell, sculptor, portrait and miniature painter, lithographer.
Scope and Contents
Letters to and from Thomas Campbell. Eighteen letters to various people, many of them drafts, nine of them to William George Spencer Cavendish, duke of Devonshire. Fifty-four letters to Campbell from various people, including eight letters from James Thomson Gibson Craig, and six letters from Charlotte Townshend Osborne, duchess of Leeds. Accompanied by miscellaneous notes, clippings, theater programs, etc. belonging to Thomas Campbell; in all, ten items.
Campbell, Thomas, 1790-1858; Devonshire, William Spencer Cavendish, Duke of, 1790-1858; Craig, James T. Gibson (James Thomson Gibson), 1799-1886; Leeds, Charlotte Townshend Osborne, duchess of, d. 1856
- Letters to Thomas Campbell, 1838 Dec 9-1839 Oct 29
  - Aberdeen, George John James Gordon, 5th earl of, 1816-1864. 2 ALS to Thomas Campbell, Haddo House, 1838 Dec 9-1839 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Courtown, James George Stopford, 3d earl of, 1794-1858. 3 ALS to Thomas Campbell, Kettering, 1831 Mar-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    On the second leaf of the letter dated Apr 8 is Thomas Campbell's draft of a letter to the Duke of Buccleuch.
  - Devonshire, William George Spencer Cavendish, 6th duke of, 1790-1858. ALS to [Thomas Campbell], London, 1836 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Erskine, J. W. 2 ALS and 1 LS to [Thomas] Campbell, [Edinburgh] and Leamington, [1834?]-37 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Erskine, John D. 3 LS to Thomas Campbell, [Edinburgh], 1831-35 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    On blank pages of the letter of Nov 9, 1835 and on a separate leaf is Thomas Campbell's draft of a reply.
  - Forbes, Miss F. AL in the third person to [Thomas Campbell], Edinburgh, 1832 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gibson Craig, James Thomson, 1799-1886. 8 ALS to [Thomas Campbell], Edinburgh and Riccarton, 1831-48 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    On the blank pages of Gibson Craig's letter of Sep 19, 1831 is a draft of Thomas Campbell's reply, partly in pencil in an unidentified hand, partly in Campbell's own hand.
  - Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846. ALS to Thomas Campbell, [London], 1834 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hope, J. A. ALS to [Thomas Campbell], Edinburgh, 1832 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Innes, Gilbert. ALS to [Thomas Campbell], Edinburgh, 1828 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lauderdale, Anthony Maitland, 10th earl of, 1785-1863. ALS to Thomas Campbell, [n.p.], [1830?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lauderdale, James Maitland, 8th earl of, 1759-1839. 2 ALS and 2 LS to [Thomas Campbell], Dunbar and Paris, 1831-33 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Leeds, Charlotte Townshend Osborne, duchess of, d. 1856. ALS and 5 AL to [Thomas Campbell], Hornby Castle [Yorkshire] and London, [1831?]-37 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - McDonald & Leslie, firm, Aberdeen. 5 letters to [Thomas Campbell], London and Aberdeen, 1842-43 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Milne, David, fl. 1833. ALS to Thomas Campbell, Coldstream, 1833 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Orme, Maria. ALS to [Thomas] Campbell, Edinburgh, 1832 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rosslyn, James St. Clair Erskine, 2d earl of, 1762-1837. ALS to [Thomas] Campbell [n.p.], 1835 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Shrewsbury, John Talbot, 16th earl of, 1791-1852. ALS to [Thomas Campbell], Ashbourne, 1835 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stopford, George Powys, 1801-1867. ALS to [Thomas Campbell], Warkton, 1833 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stopford, James George, 1794-1858
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Courtown, James George Stopford, 3d earl of
  - Sutherland, George Granville Leveson-Cower, 2d duke of, 1786-1861. 3 ALS to [Thomas Campbell], [London] and Lilleshall [Shropshire], 1836-38 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Accompanied by list giving the measurement of three statues.
  - Tytler, Patrick Fraser, 1791-1849. 3 ALS to Thomas Campbell, 1829-31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified. 3 ALS to Thomas Campbell, 1826-51 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letters from Thomas Campbell, 1831 Aug 29
  - [Committee for Procuring a Statue of the Duke of York.] Note (draft, in an unidentified hand) in the third person to, 1831 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Written inside wrapper addressed to himself in hand of Lord Lauderdale. Accompanied by a report from the committee, written in an unidentified hand, dated May 12, 1835.
  - Devonshire, William George Spencer Cavendish, 6th duke of, 1790-1858. 9 letters (drafts and copies, partly autograph and partly in several unidentified hands), 1835-37 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gibson Craig, James Thomson, 1799-1886. Letter (in the hand of an amanuensis), 1838 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846. AL (draft), [London], [1834 Mar?] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Holland, Henry Richard Vassall, Baron, 1773-1840. Letter (copy in an unidentified hand), [London], 1838 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lauderdale, James Maitland, 8th earl of, 1759-1839. AL and letter in an unidentified hand (drafts), [n.p.], [1836 Sep 10], 1838 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Leeds, Charlotte Townshend Osborne, duchess of, d. 1856. 2 letters (draft, in an unidentified hand), [n.p.], [1835] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - [Mansfield, Mr.?] AL (draft), [n.p.], [1836? Sep 10] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Other Papers, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clippings, 1812, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Theater programs, 1850, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)